Finding Aid for Joseph L. Sax Papers, 1943-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- that vested interests not be included in such a way that they could interfere with an excellent decision-making process ...
On April 1st, 1969 Anderson introduced the original bill. It was labeled H.B. 3055 and was referred to the House Committee on Conservation and Recreation. Soon thereafter the first official comment on the bill was made. On April 21st, 1969, the Attorney General, Frank Kelley, issued an analysis that raised the problem of spurious suits under the act and argued that court action would now be substituted for preferable informal administrative conferences. Whether this was actually the position of the Attorney General himself became a significant political question in later months, as Mr. Kelley was later to state that this memo or bill analysis was incorrect, that he always supported the type of legislation that MEPA represented.
Representative Anderson was not always confident, especially in the first months of its consideration, that MEPA would become law. In November, 1969, he wrote that the bill could not pass in its current form. In fact, Anderson made several comments early on that indicated he was skeptical about the wisdom of the enactment of the bill's original version.
Major activity in the State Legislature on the bill did not begin until 1970. January of that year saw the first set of commentaries on the Act, both official forms and in correspondence and memoranda to and from Representative Anderson and other members of the Michigan Legislature.
Public comment began on January 21st, 1970, in Lansing. On that day 31 people testified at a public hearing on the bill. Present were Professor Sax, representatives of the Audubon Society, the Michigan United Conservation Clubs, the Department of Natural Resources, the Pesticides Council, Detroit Edison, ENACT, the United Auto Workers, the Sierra Club, the Jaycees, the Wilderness Society, the Michigan Department of Agriculture, the PTA, and a variety of ad hoc environmental organizations. Many of these latter informal groups were represented by Mrs. Wolfe.
In what was later described by Representative Anderson as a 11complete explanation of the bill," Sax summarized the legislation and the rationale for its consideration. He spoke first of the "capture" of administrative agencies by the very interests that they were supposed to be regulating or managing. He argued that the Administrative Procedures Act was not enough to ensure the protection by the state bureaucracy of important natural resources, and he defended the notion of the private attorney general. Recognizing as probable, the assertion that a court was an improper institution for addressing environmental problems, Sax defended the ability of the courts to handle complex scientific and technical matters and explained the reason for putting the burden of discussing alternatives on the defendant. lie argued that the defendant should have considered alternatives already -- before acting in a way that jeopardized the natural environment. He discussed why the prima facie requirement was written as it was -- asserting that it would eliminate frivolous cases. In addition the allocation of costs under the act and the expense of litigation would discourage spurious litigation.
Professor William Pierce also of the University of Michigan Law School played an important role throughout the early months of 1970 by providing legal analysis supportive of the bill. Initially, he opposed the alternative to the use of citizen environmental lawsuits of creation of a 3-man environmental board. This was an idea discussed often and in several quarters in the late 1960's.
Other important events in the struggle for life of the MEPA occurred in January. The State Chamber of Commerce published a highly critical analysis of the bill while a favorable bill analysis was issued by the Department of Natural Resources. Government agencies in Lansing were not in agreement over the bill however. A member of the Air Pollution Control Commission, Richard A. Rasmussen, argued (in a letter) that the proposed act would duplicate the effort of the agency. He added that considerable competence existed in the state bureaucracy.
The first DNR analysis contended that frivolous lawsuits could be barred and that costs could be assessed against the plaintiff in MEPA litigation. It was in this evaluation by the DNR that the agency recommended that a prima facie determination that damage had occurred should be required before any "restrictive" or injunctive relief could be given. The agency proposed a master or a 3-man environmental review board either appointed by the governor or established by the legislature. DNR also suggested that the plaintiff be required to prove that he had exhausted all his administrative avenues of relief before bringing a lawsuit under the act.
An important analysis of the bill was made by Joseph Thibodeau, the Governor's legal advisor. Thibodeau, who was to play an active role throughout consideration of the bill, addressed several points in a memorandum of January 26, 1970. He argued that existing standards should control whether the agency has given adequate consideration to protection of the environment. Further he warned that it would be unwise for intervenors to be able to sit on their rights." "Pollution," "impairment," and "destruction," and other terms such as "reasonably likely" and "feasible and prudent alternative" needed to be more clearly defined in the bill. Thibodeau's analysis also discussed devices for preventing frivolous suits, clarification of the definition of prima facie in the bill and the shifting of the burden to the defendant, Importantly, the argument was also made that the exhaustion of administrative remedies doctrine should not be superseded by this legislation.
By the end of January considerable private industry sentiment on H.B. 3055 had been aired. Companies of all sizes began to petition the legislature with their worries about the bill. These varied from concern over the burden of proof to predictions of the overburdening of the judiciary. Also industry felt that a defendant who was in compliance with existing standards set by an agency and who was employing the best available technology should not be subject to citizen environmental lawsuits. Economic burdens on industry that the act might generate were also described. The Chamber of Commerce made many of these arguments throughout the bill's movement through the State legislature but the companies themselves expressed their views directly, as well. The Motor Wheel Corporation, the Abitibi Corporation, Detroit Edison, Park, Davis & Company, Consumers Power Company, and Chrysler Corporation were among those which submitted written comments to Anderson or other members of the House.
Not all support for the legislation came from the liberal coalition that later developed for passage. A University of Michigan Law School professor wrote that the act was desirable because it increased the ability of the middle-class to protect the environment in light of the local government administration's preoccupation with welfare concerns. Professor White also argued, in a letter to a Republican legislator, that no frivolous lawsuits or "half-baked" injunctions would result.
Representative Anderson in these early months of 1970 indicated that he was sensitive to the problem of the frivolous suit. He saw a need to protect those industries that had already been the subject of control or management by administrative agencies and those that were complying with existing standards. His concerns led him to seek from legal experts analyses addressing res judicata, vagueness in the Act's language, and exhaustion of administrative remedies. Anderson assured potential defendants that they would not be harassed by citizens. These efforts were not confined to the private sector; in a letter to the Director of the Department of Natural Resources he stated that the act would not be abused by citizens in litigation against the agency.
In February Senator Vander Laan suggested that suits should be reviewed or screened by the Attorney General, an idea that was to be mentioned often by opponents of direct citizen involvement, including government agencies such as the Water Resources Commission. It was in February as well that the first large public hearing on the bill was held.
A vocal group testified in Grand Rapids. Almost 500 people were in attendance. Comment on the legislation was mostly favorable although some negative analyses were made by members of the agricultural community. Represented were area colleges, the League of Women Voters, small groups such as the North Ottawa Road and Gun Club, the Western Michigan Chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union, the West Michigan Chapter of Trout Unlimited, the Michigan Division of the Izaak Walton League and the Save our Lakes Committee, Inc.
It was in February as well that a highly unfavorable analysis of the law in its original form was made by the Michigan Chamber of Commerce. The Chamber offered several arguments against the bill and proposed a number of changes. Among these were the requirement of a mechanism for a leave to commence a civil action-to be reviewed by the Attorney General. The Attorney General would then have the power to dismiss the complaint. In its extensive commentary the Chamber also made the following points: the plaintiff should have to prove that the defendant is not in compliance with an existing standard; if technology to control pollution does not exist the defendant should not be found in violation of the act; if no feasible or prudent alternative existed to the defendant's action, the suit should be dismissed; venue should be where the defendant resides or has his principal place of business; a security bond should be required; definitions of pollution, "impairment" and other terms used in the legislation should be refined; the qualifications of the master should be determined; administrative proceedings should be made mandatory for the plaintiff if they are available; and the standards as to a prima facie case should be specified. The Attorney General also expressed in late February (in a letter) his support for the principle encompassed in the bill but his continued concern for spurious suits.
In March more public hearings were held -- in Macomb County and in Ann Arbor. And interest groups began extensive campaigns for passage. The United Auto Workers encouraged large turnouts at public hearings. The union also reportedly found a way to "handle Kelley"--a reference to labor's ability to influence the Attorney General to support the legislation. Increasing interest in the bill -was evidenced by the fact that by mid-month Anderson had received over 3000 letters in support of the act.
The Department of Natural Resources issued another analysis of the bill. Its only suggestion now was that a technically qualified person should aver an actual threat to the environment before litigation could take place. The DNR position continued to be at odds with that of the State Department of Public Health, Michigan Air Pollution Control Commission. The latter agency feared "excess" litigation and argued that the bill ignored the doctrine of separation of powers and enabled courts to act not only in a judicial but in executive and legislative capacities as well. After arguing for agency superiority in resolving environmental problems, the health agency advocated an amendment that would make acceptance of a suit discretionary with a court and would have the plaintiff first exhaust all administrative remedies. The State Chamber of Commerce continued to suggest amendments. So, too, did the Water Resources Commission whose position on the bill was never as favorable as its counterpart, the Department of Natural Resources.
Events in March were highly favorable to passage of the act. The Governor announced before 12,000 people at an environmental teach-in at the University of Michigan that he would support the act if certain "alterations" were made. The Attorney General now argued that his 1969 memo opposing the bill was in error. As well after the public hearing in Macomb County with a light turnout (only 33 persons testified and opposition was expressed--primarily by the mushroom growers and big farmers) a pro-MEPA crowd dominated a hearing in Wyoming, Michigan. On March 26th, 2-1/2 hours of testimony were heard by the House Conservation and Recreation Committee. Attending were Senator Levin, Representative Vander Laan, Joan Wolfe and over 400 citizens. The following day Senator Levin attacked Governor Milliken alleging that the Governor did not fully support the legislation. Levin announced that he was introducing with Senator Bursley a bill identical to H.B. 3055 in the Senate. Soon thereafter the Governor announced that he did not only "endorse and support" the bill but that he would "actively work for" its passage.
Despite this political support, on March 25th, an analysis by Joseph Thibodeau was made a substitute bill to H.B. 3055 in the House Committee on Conservation and Recreation. The bill was reported out of committee with the recommendation that it pass. This motion carried 11-1. (It was at this point that Representative Goemaere made a motion to name the bill the Anderson Environmental Protection Act. This motion also carried by a vote of 11-1.) The substitute was taken from a Thibodeau memorandum of I-larch 18th, 1970 to Representatives Anderson and Goemaere. The Governor's legal adviser argued at great length for the elimination of the provision that suit be brought in the name of the state, for circumscribing agency power under the Act, against the public trust language, for greater specificity as to the defenses of feasible and prudent alternative, for the addition of the descriptive adjective "appropriate" before "temporary relief", for a venue provision and for several other changes-ranging from impleader rights to constitutional challenges.
The analysis did not go unanswered by Professor Sax. In a long memorandum by him, Professor Pierce and Mr. Irvin entitled "Thoughts on H.B. 3055" Sax soon addressed several concerns in the Thibodeau memorandum. Sax noted that exhaustion of administrative
remedies was not only not necessary but in many times futile. He explained the existence of the language on "feasible and prudent alternatives". Sax's memorandum spelled out the meaning of the public trust and argued again that the courts were quite capable of handling the types of complex issues that would arise under the MEPA. Sax and his colleagues also noted that the language "in the name of the State" had been included to assure the court that it was entertaining a case or controversy. Furthermore, the right of individual government agencies to sue one another was essential according to the rebuttal. These "Thoughts" also addressed other procedural provisions in the MEPA and emphasized the flexibility of a common law approach to the protection of natural resources. (Emphasizing common law was not surprising in light of Sax's understanding of the changes that MEPA would create. Later (June 1970) Sax described the MEPA in a letter to the press as "analogous to the creation of the right of privacy.. ."[4])
These memoranda, extensive analyses by private citizens and several Michigan attorneys and law professors were among the high lights of the legal treatment of the Act. While some commentators have pointed out that the MEPA's passage was primarily a political result, considerably detailed and generally high quality legal
Not all groups thought that the bill was strong enough in any form considered. Testimony by the United Auto Workers, in fact, advocated an act with fewer obstacles to citizen action. Specifically, the union argued that the cost apportionment provision of the statute might be an excessive burden on plaintiffs, inhibiting litigation.
April was a month both of compromise and of intense struggle over amendments. Early in the month Sax wrote in a letter that he found "cleaning up amendments" acceptable in order to gain the full support of the Governor. Other positive news for proponents of the act included another analysis by the Department of Natural Resources--now unequivocally supporting the legislation. The DNR position was crucial because the department was understood to be a potential defendant in cases brought under the statute. It was in mid-April as well that the Governor wrote to the Environmental. Action Council indicating that he shared fully its interest in passage of the legislation.
Nonetheless, the movement toward passage of a strong citizen suit law suffered several setbacks in April. Representative Ford noted the possibility of industry being driven from the state by the existence of the legislation, and other elected officials articulated possible problems with the law. Late an amendment to remove the descriptive adjective "unreasonable" from the bill. This term had been added in an amendment and while some argued that its import was not great, others felt that restricting liability to actions that were "unreasonable" was a strong limiting factor on the statute.
The language came from the earlier Thibodeau analysis that recommended insertion of the word "unreasonable" before the phrase "pollution, impairment or destruction" wherever it appeared in the bill. When first considered in late March the vote to remove this modifier from the bill fell just two votes short. It was not until April 27 that the amendment deleting "unreasonable" and "unreasonably" was passed by securing 56 votes, exactly the number needed for passage. Five Republicans, T. Brown, Kok (who had been originally approached to introduce the bill), Sackett, Sneekens, and Varnun, joined with Democrats to produce this victory for proponents of the act, All Democrats voted for the bill. It was in this same session that the legislation passed in the house by a resounding 98-3 vote. [5]
Two protests that followed indicate in some detail the concerns of the opposition. Representative Swallow declared:
While I subscribe to this bill in principle, I voted no so I might afford myself the opportunity to protest the removal from the bill the word "unreasonable"... I see in my own community a possible effect of this bill that could terminate the employment of 500 persons. I believe that the court, in administering this bill, should be provided some latitude so as to permit a reasonable degree of tolerable pollution...
Representative Allen made an argument for an alternative approach to pollution control:
I voted against House Bill No. 3055 because I firmly believe it is a step in the wrong direction in the battle against pollution. In my opinion the fight will require professionals such as biologists, chemists, engineers and ecologists... it seems to me inappropriate to expect the judiciary to determine the tolerance levels. Every citizen in Michigan fully aware of his day's activities and with a thorough knowledge of the law should be able to go to bed at night fairly certain whether that day's activities may tomorrow land him in court charged and later convicted of a serious breach of law. Ladies and gentlemen, if H.B. 3055 becomes law, no Michigan citizen in the future can go to bed with such a feeling of security.
The forum for consideration of MEPA then moved to the Michigan Senate. Here also the debate was emotional and vigorously fought. In the Senate Conservation Committee's public hearing on May 12th? the concerns of the proponents were argued forcefully (the major opponents of the bill were not present). Keynote testimony was presented by AFL-CIO President and DNR Commissioner August Scholle. He stated: "I plead with you to take this first step for posterity, mankind and our grandchildren--give them a chance." Doctor Paul Herbert, a retired Michigan State University Professor, testified with a heart pill in his hand: "As I listen to you talk here I thought I was coming down with a second heart attack. I challenge you to pass the bill. If something is wrong you know industry is going to scream and you'll come back and correct it next year." Senator Harvey Lodge, a Republican, retorted by charging that Michigan's 8 million residents were responsible for pollution--a theme he repeated several times in exchanges with members of the audience.
Opponents of the MEPA in its existing form presented their major challenge in the Senate Conservation and Tourist Industry Committee on the following day. The State Chamber of Commerce described language in the bill as vague and indefinite, challenged the absence of specific standards, and requested that the word $'unreasonable" be reintroduced into the bill. The Michigan Manufacturers' Association argued for a security bond of $3000. This group also advocated that no temporary relief be allowed until a prima facie case was established and argued that the affirmative defenses noted in the bill should be made in the alternative-substituting "or" for "and" in Section 3(l). The Association, speaking through Dwight Vincent, suggested strongly that a better approach to environmental protection is through administrative regulation. Vincent favored the establishment of a "comprehensive ecology program" through a Department of Life and Ecology.
A flurry of activity followed the Senate Conservation and Tourist Committee hearing. Representative Anderson sent out a mailing to 5000 correspondents who had expressed interest in the bill. He requested that they contact their Senators to urge favorable attention to TMEPA. The League of Women Voters announced its support for the legislation. The Farm Bureau wrote an unfavorable bill analysis. The Governor by this time expressed his willingness to "push the bill". He indicated that he thought that chances for enactment might improve if the bill were added to another bill strengthening the Water Resources Commission and the Air Pollution Control Commission. The State Chamber carried out a widespread mailing leveling several objections to the House language. The Chamber described the movement toward passage: "Accelerated pressures and dramatized hysteria created by the neo-politics of later hour dilettante earth savers." Not all business interests opposed the bill. A construction company wrote (to Representative Anderson) that it opposed the State Chamber position and that business could live with the Act.
It was June, 1970. Early in the month the Senate acted to critically weaken the act. Yet by the end of June it had passed the bill in an unscathed form which was immediately acceptable to the House and which became the Michigan Environmental Protection Act.